{"tossups": [{"question": "This monarch died at Newark Castle during a conflict with Robert Fitzwalter called the First Barons\u2019War. This king feuded with Pope Innocent III over his appointment of Stephen Langton to the post of Archbishop of Canterbury. This ruler, who was nicknamed \u201cLackland,\u201d negotiated a legal document with a group of rebellious noblemen at a meadow at Runnymede. For ten points, name this ruler, the only English king of his name, who signed the Magna Carta in 1215.", "answer": "<b> John</b> (or<b> John</b> Lackland; accept<b> John</b> I)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was killed by Tomyris, a female leader of the Massagetae, after he treacherously attacked her. This ruler conquered Media and Lydia and, after destroying the Neo-Babylonian Empire, he gave himself the title of King of Kings, or<em> shahanshah</em>. Alexander the Great visited this man\u2019s tomb in his capital, Persepolis. For ten points, name this \u201cGreat\u201d founder of the Persian Empire.", "answer": "<b> Cyrus</b> the Great (or<b> Cyrus</b> II)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this American-based petroleum company founded by John D. Rockefeller.", "answer": "<b> Standard Oil</b> Company", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One of its leaders ordered the assassination of Ivan Stambolic and was targeted by a 1999 NATO bombing. Kosovo\u2019s independence from this state has not yet formally been recognized by much of the world. Slobodan Milosevic once ruled, for ten points, what former Yugoslavian republic that lost its access to the sea after the 2006 secession of Montenegro but maintains its capital at Belgrade?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Serbia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "John Ingram served as the final leader of this movement. One side in this event coaxed the Occaneechi into attacking the Susquehannock and vandalized the Green Spring estate. This rebellion, which ended when its leader died of dysentery, was prompted by governor William Berkeley\u2019s failure to address fears of Indian attack. Jamestown was burnt during, for ten points, what 1676 rebellion of disgruntled Virginian settlers?", "answer": "Nathaniel<b> Bacon</b>\u2019s Rebellion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A set of \u201cscrolls\u201d were discovered near, for ten points, what salty body of water bordered by Jordan, the West Bank, and Israel?", "answer": "<b> Dead</b> Sea", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "An opera by this man is based on a real-life incident recorded in the<em> Divine Comedy</em> in which the title man impersonated Buoso Donati. The aria \u201cO mio babbino caro\u201d is from this composer\u2019s<em> Gianni Schicchi</em> [skee-kee]. In another of his operas, a character is often introduced with the \u201cStar-Spangled Banner\u201d and marries a woman who sings \u201cUn bel di\u201d and commits seppuku. For ten points, name this Italian composer who depicted Lieutenant Pinkerton and Cio-Cio San [cho-cho sahn] in his<em> Madame Butterfly</em>?", "answer": "Giacomo<b> Puccini</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s ruling party has been accused of holding slush funds through Senator Luis Barcenas\u2019Swiss bank accounts. The leadership of this country\u2019s Socialist Worker\u2019s Party is vacant after a dispute with Susana Diaz led Pedro Sanchez to resign. In October 2016, this country\u2019s Prime Minister, Mariano Rajoy of the People\u2019s Party, was sworn in for a second term after a 10-month period of political deadlock. For ten points, name this Iberian country whose capital is Madrid.", "answer": "<b> Spain</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This case was cited a decade later in<em> Griffin v. Prince Edward County</em>, which forbade a plank of the\u201cStanley plan\u201d calling for a voucher system. Those vouchers were part of Harry Byrd\u2019s plan of \u201cmassive resistance\u201d against this Supreme Court ruling, which was decided unanimously. Thurgood Marshall argued for the NAACP in this case, which overturned<em> Plessy v. Ferguson</em>. For ten points, name this 1954 case that declared \u201cseparate but equal\u201d segregation of public schools unconstitutional.", "answer": "<b> Brown</b> v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was put in charge of an economic and rearmament program called the Four Year Plan. This man\u2019s chief of staff, Karl Koller, convinced him to write a telegram asking for a transfer of power. After the failure of Eagle Day, a large air assault ordered by this man, he began a system of strategic bombing called the Blitz. This man committed suicide the day before his execution, which had been ordered by the Nuremberg Trials. For ten points, name this head of the Luftwaffe and right hand man of Adolf Hitler.", "answer": "Hermann<b> G\u00a8oring</b> [ger-ing]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Santa Clara County\u2019s 1886 lawsuit against a corporation of this type was relied upon by the Supreme Court in the<em> Citizens United</em> decision. John MacDonald resigned as the first Canadian Prime Minister due to bribes from this industry. One cartoon depicted a man in this profession rolling bowling balls down Wall Street after the Panic of 1873; that man, Jay Gould, took over the Union Pacific company in this industry. For ten points, name this lucrative 19th-century business conducted by the Southern Pacific, Central Pacific, and Union Pacific lines.", "answer": "<b> rail</b>roads", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This general liberated a set of ten cities known as the Decapolis as part of the reorganization of the eastern provinces. He was appointed to fight Mithradates VI in Asia Minor after his successful, six-week campaign against the Cilician pirates. This man was killed by Ptolemy XIII after his defeat in a civil war where he squandered his advantage from the Siege of Dyrrachium and lost the decisive Battle of Pharsalus. For ten points, name this member of the First Triumvirate and rival of Julius Caesar.", "answer": "<b> Pompey</b> the Great (or Gnaeus<b> Pompeius</b> Magnus)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this city that was destroyed in a Great Fire, the capital of England.", "answer": "<b> London</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This businessman is named Secretary of the Interior in Philip Roth\u2019s<em> The Plot Against America</em>. A product made by this man\u2019s company is taken as the name of a Betelgeusian alien who saves Arthur Dent from the destruction of Earth in<em> The Hitchhiker\u2019s Guide to the Galaxy</em>. In Aldous Huxley\u2019s<em> Brave New</em> <em>World</em>, years are dated back to the year that this man\u2019s company first produced the Model T. For ten points, name this American automobile manufacturer.", "answer": "Henry<b> Ford</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man wrote a now-lost manuscript to Edmond Halley about \u201cthe motion of bodies in an orbit.\u201dA constant sometimes named for this man was first measured using a torsion balance by Henry Cavendish and is written as big G. One law named for this man technically says that the derivative of momentum with respect to time is equal to the force, but is more commonly written  <em>F</em> =<em> ma</em>  [F equals m times a]. For ten points, name this English physicist and namesake of three laws of motion.", "answer": "Sir Isaac<b> Newton</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This organization operates the connected Sackler and Freer Galleries of Art. As of November 2016, this organization has run two successful Kickstarter campaigns, raising</b> <b>funds to preserve (+)</b> <b>Judy Garland\u2019s ruby slippers from</b><em><b> The Wizard of Oz</b></em><b> and Neil</b> <b>Armstrong\u2019s</b><em><b> Apollo 11</b></em> <b>spacesuit, which were each donated to this organization. The (*) </b>National Mall is the home of 11 facilities run by this organization, including one devoted to Air and Space. For ten points, name this group of American historical museums that is largely centered in Washington, D.C.", "answer": "<b> Smithsonian</b> Institution", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This city\u2019s Mill Pond, once part of an Atlantic harbor, was filled in in the 19th century to create Bullfinch Triangle and a Haymarket Square. Other land reclamation projects in this city created the Back Bay neighborhood and lowered (+) Beacon Hill. The 15-year-long\u201cBig Dig\u201d constructed the Central Artery of I-93 through this city and brought I-90 past (*) </b> Logan International Airport. The Freedom Trail passes by the Old North Church and Fanueil Hall in, for ten points, what capital city of Massachusetts?", "answer": "<b> Boston</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>An army fighting for a king of this name lost the Battle of St. Quentin, after which he accepted the Peace of Cateau-Cambresis; that second French king of this name died shortly thereafter in a jousting exhibition. A war between (+) three prospective rulers of this name forms the core of the French Wars of Religion. A monarch of this name said (*)</b> \u201cParis is well worth a mass\u201d in his conversion to Catholicism. For ten points, name this common name of French kings, the fourth of whom founded the House of Bourbon.", "answer": "<b> Henry</b> (accept<b> Henry</b> II, the War of the Three<b> Henry</b>s,<b> Henry</b> IV)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The history and end of this policy are recounted in</b><em><b> My Traitor\u2019s Heart</b></em><b>, written by the exiled Rian Malan. A person who was imprisoned because of this policy documented his (+) incarceration in the book</b><em><b> Long Walk to Freedom</b></em><b>. The breakdown of this policy provides the backdrop of Nadine Gordimer\u2019s novel</b><em><b> July\u2019s People</b></em><b>, in which the Smales family flees from (*)</b> Johannesburg. Nelson Mandela opposed, for ten points, what discriminatory policy of South Africa?", "answer": "<b> Apartheid</b> (prompt on descriptive answers that don\u2019t use the word Apartheid)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A rumor that home-based conscripts in this nation would be sent overseas triggered</b> <b>the Terrace Mutiny. William Lyon Mackenzie King dealt with a 1944 conscription</b> <b>crisis in this country, which hosted the signing of the (+)</b> <b>Atlantic Charter. Forces</b> <b>from this nation launched the Dieppe Raid and made up most of the soldiers landing</b> <b>on (*)</b> Juno Beach during D-Day. For ten points, name this Allied country that fought in World War II alongside its southern neighbor, the United States.", "answer": "<b> Canada</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}